Zeeshan Raza

Phone: 07411435522 Address: 59 Cobden Road, E11 3PE, London

Summary

I build web applications with advanced frontend and backend skills with over 15 years of commercial experience using a wide range of technologies including JavaScript (AngularJS, NodeJS, JQuery, D3), HTML5, CSS3 (LESS, SASS), PHP (Laravel, Lumen, Zend Framework, Slim), Java, REST APIs (developing/consuming), MySQL and NoSQL databases, Firebase (Realtime BaaS), Parse (BaaS) using both traditional waterfall and agile practices.

I have very good knowledge of Object Oriented Programming and ability to create testable (TDD,BDD) decoupled components. With my dedicated and "can-do" attitude, I always want to learn new technologies and find a practical application at work which provide solid grounding for a development lead role.

I am Certified ScrumMaster and Zend Certified Engineer (PHP5) and hold Masters degree in Computer Science.

Work experience

Elektron Technology

January 2016 — September 2016

Senior Front-end Developer

My role was to build AngularJS application talking to LoopBack(MEAN) based REST API using CSS3 (SASS), HTML5, angular-nvd3 (Angular D3), Gulp, Git, Bower, etc.; producing testable code using both TDD (Karma/Jasmine, ES6) and BDD (CucumberJs, ES6) approaches in Agile environment.

Worked with product owner to ensure good communication and UX designer for quick prototyping and to deliver working software to business. The communications between product owner and tester worked really well to ensure the understanding of the requirement and delivering the desired functionality without any surprises on last day of the sprint.

Attended code reviews and provided knowledge and support for creating a SOLID code base.

Cambridge Satchel Company

November 2014 — January 2016

Lead Front-end Developer

My role was to build AngularJS, mobile first SPA with reusable, modular (John Papa Style Guide), SOLID architecture, completely decoupled business logic from DOM, talking to RESTful APIs, using ionicframework, HTML5, LESS/SASS, Gulp, Git, Bower in Agile environment.

Created AngularJS frontend for a Christmas advent calendar using "Angular Material Design" and Parse.com as RESTful backend.

Created AngularJS Orders module to manage order life cycle from getting new orders to find products in the warehouse, customization and manage deliveries. The application communicate with the Mule REST API to manage orders and MetaPack for creating consignments and printing labels.

Created AngularJS realtime Stock module to manage company stocks in realtime using Firebase and Mule REST API for data persistence.

Created AngularJS Products module to create/manage products talking to Mule REST API for data persistence .

Zeeshan Raza

After almost one year of development, the application has changed the way company was working; from last year chaos and having many unhappy clients during busy periods (BlackFriday/Christmas) to meet delivery promises with smooth orders management, realtime stocks, and super easy/consistent process of creating/maintaining products.

The application is heavily using promises, Angular UI router, Angular bindings, directives, providers, services, modules, filters and is covered cross browser BDD tests using protractor. The development setup includes tasks automation using Gulp and Bower for frontend package management.

Euromoney Institutional Investor

April 2012 — November 2014

Development Manager

Leading onshore and offshore development teams using scrum methodology. Responsible for technical direction and leadership, implementation of best practices and optimal design patterns, streamlined frontend development process using modern technologies (Gulp, Bower and others)

Creating quick responsive/adaptive prototypes using AngularJS/Bootstrap/Mocked data for visual concepts and interactions with intention to integrate with final code base with minimal changes.

Leading PHP team to build high performing back office application to input over 15,000 financial products everyday to existing 8m, with over 50 properties and 14 relations.

Structured Retail Products

June 2008 — April 2012

Systems Developer

Working as part of a small agile team of developers, my role was consist of frontend development utilizing hand written responsive CSS, and JavaScript (JQuery, Handlebars) to build dashboard functionality which can help subscriber to customize their home page and drop apps (widgets) from the site onto their dashboard and apply filters or group data to see data in different dimensions.

I was also responsible of full rewrite of user management/subscription module using PHP (Zend Framework, PHPTaI) and building RESTful API to expose huge financial data (over 8m products).

Saudi Oger Limited

November 2004 — April 2008

Web Developer

I was responsible for designing and building in-house "Staff Holiday Manager" with multilingual support (English/Arabic), using Java, Oracle and JavaScript (jQuery). The system allows to coordinate staff holiday leave, track annual leave entitlement, manage employee leave requests online and create "exit application" for Saudi Interior Ministry. I was responsible for end-to-end application development process including analysis, design, development, testing, release and staff training.

Tower Technologies (Pvt.) Limited

April 2001 — November 2004

Sr. Software Engineer

I was part of team of Java and front-end developers.

Skills

Frontend Technologies

JavaScript (AngularJs, Angular Material Design, Bootstrap, jQuery, Jasmine, Protractor, Mocha, Ionic Framework, Titanium Appcelerator, D3), CSS3 (LESS, SASS, Bootstrap, Foundation)

Backend Technologies

PHP (Laravel, Lumen, Zend Framework, Slim), Java, .Net (very basic)

Databases

MySQL, SQLite, DBaaS (Parse.com, Firebase)

Experiential Knowledge

Zeeshan Raza 2

Angular 2, TypeScript, React

Other Tools and Technologies

REST APIs (Developing/Using), Cloud, Hybrid App Development, Grunt, Gulp, Bower, Yeoman, GIT / SVN, Sublime Text, Jira, Confluence, Browser-Sync

Certifications

- Certified ScrumMaster (https://www.scrumalliance.org/community/profile/zraza3)
- Zend Certified Engineer PHP5 (http://www.zend.com/en/yellow-pages/ZEND012965)

Education

Masters (MS) in Computer Science

1999 - 2000

Punjab Institute of Computer Sciences Lahore - Pakistan

Bachelor of Science (BSc), Mathematics, Physics

1996 - 1998

Govt. FC College, Lahore - Pakistan

References

References available upon request.

Zeeshan Raza